Okay בוקר טוב. boker tov. Today's דף daf is
ל"ה lamed hey and today's דף daf is דף ל"ה. daf lamed
hey. We pick up in the middle of ל"ד עמוד ב' lamed
dalet amud bet
and we are at the אמר רב הונא. Amar Rav Huna. It's
like about 20 lines down, about two-fifths of the way down. There's
an asterisk at the end of the line. Line starts with the
word רב הונא. Rav Huna. So five, ten, fifteen, yeah, about exactly
20 lines down. Okay, so אמר רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna, says
Rav Huna. So we've been dealing with the whole case in the
משנה, mishna, which is if somebody pays, or as the גמרא Gemara
modifies it, agrees to pay, there and then the גנב ganav is
found. A שומר shomer agrees to pay, and even if the שומר
shomer according to his own admission is liable, so he's paying just
and his whole צדקות tzidkus he's doing is he's not swearing falsely
based on his own admission, or he's not making us שלעפ shlep
him to court. Anyway, so if he pays or agrees to pay
and then the גנב ganav is found, the שומר shomer gets כפל.
kefal. That's done as a type of way of incentivizing him, moving
things along, ensuring that the owner will get back his principal, which
is what the owner's primarily concerned about, and that's the basic principle
of the משנה. mishna. So now the גמרא Gemara shifts gears a
little bit from the idea that the שומר shomer gets כפל kefal
when he agrees to pay to look at this question about wait,
when he agrees to pay, presumably one reason he'd want to pay,
and at least nowadays we have this and it's already rooted in
the גמרא, Gemara, this like strong sensibility that people don't want to
take a שבועה. shvua. People shouldn't even take a שבועת אמת shvua
she'emes let alone שבועת שקר. shvua sheker. So, you know, you would
imagine one of the reasons he might want to pay is he
might want to just say I don't want to take a שבועה,
shvua, just take the money fine, maybe just wants to do it
because he's a good guy, maybe he's doing it because as we
said he's being honest because to take a שבועה shvua would be
to take a שבועה shvua falsely. Anyway, comes along רב הונא Rav
Huna and רב הונא Rav Huna says it's all very nice and
the owner gets his money back and it's going to be כפל,
kefal, the שומר's shomer going to get his כפל, kefal, but maybe
the שומר shomer is still lying. How could the שומר shomer be
lying if the שומר's shomer paying? Because maybe he still has the
object and he's doing this because he really wants this object. Okay,
so that's what רב הונא Rav Huna comes to introduce and tell
us that the שומר shomer will never get out of taking a
שבועה. shvua. So let's take a look. אמר רב הונא משביעין ליה
שבועה שאינו ברשותו. Amar Rav Huna mashvinan lei shvua she'eino birshuso.
Even if he agrees to pay, you make him take an oath
that the object is still not in his possession. מאי טעמא Mai
ta'ama why? חיישינן שמא עיניו נתן בה. Chashinan shema einov nasan bah.
We're afraid that he's put his eye on it, meaning that he's
coveted it and he's trying to take it for himself.
Right, so clearly this whole incentive, you're not going to get out
of a שבועה shvua regardless. מיתיבי. Maisei. Now let's challenge this. Now
we're going to focus on רב הונא Rav Huna and sort of
move away from our משנה mishna for a bit. המלווה את חבירו
על המשכון. Hamalveh es chaveiro al hamashkon.
So you lend money to your friend and he gives you a
piece of collateral. You lend him, you know, five hundred dollars and
he gives you his iPhone. Okay, my good old iPhone. Okay, so
ואבד המשכון ve'avad hamashkon
and then the iPhone was lost. ואמר לו סלע הלוויתיך עליו שקל
היה שווה. Ve'amar lo sela hivvisicha alav shekel hayah shaveh.
And I the loan, I'm the one who lent the money, so
I'm liable for the loss of the משכון, mashkon, I'm essentially a
שומר shomer on the משכון. mashkon. So the value of the משכון
mashkon that's lost is going to be deducted from the money the
guy owes me. So I said look, I lent you a thousand
dollars but it was only... I lent you five hundred dollars but
it was like an old iPhone and it had a cracked screen
and it was only worth two hundred and fifty. So you still
owe me two hundred and fifty dollars. והלה אומר לא כי סלע
הלוויתני עליו סלע היה שווה. Ve'halah omer lo ki sela hivvisani alav
sela hayah shaveh. No,
you lent me five hundred dollars, it was a brand new iPhone,
it was worth five hundred dollars, so I don't owe you anything.
Okay, so basically you got it? We're deducting the loss of the
object from the money that's owed. I the lender am the one
that is the שומר shomer on the object. Okay, and basically I
am saying... and we're debating now how much the object was worth.
So what's the הלכה? halacha? So the משנה mishna says, or the
ברייתא braisa says or whatever, I forget which it is, anyway, והלה
אומר לא כי סלע סלע פטור. ve'halah omer lo ki sela sela
patur. So basically that's a case of כופר הכל, kofer hakol, right?
I say you still owe me two hundred and fifty dollars and
you say no, I owe you zero because the iPhone was worth
the full amount of the loan. So it's כופר הכל kofer hakol
and you're פטור patur from an oath. Now if I
say
סלע הלוויתיך עליו שקל היה שווה. sela hivvisicha alav shekel hayah shaveh.
Now again, I say I lent you
five hundred, it was worth
two hundred and fifty. והלה אומר לא כי סלע הלוויתני עליו שלושה
דינרים היה שווה. Ve'halah omer lo ki sela hivvisani alav sheloshah dinarim
hayah shaveh. No, it was worth... I lent you a hundred and
it was worth seventy-five. So I only owe you twenty-five dollars, not
the fifty dollars that you're claiming I still owe you. So the
גמרא Gemara says
חייב, chayav, and that's מודה במקצת modeh bemiktzas because effectively I'm saying
you still owe me fifty dollars and you're saying no, I only
owe you
twenty-five dollars. That's מודה במקצת. modeh bemiktzas. סלע הלוויתיך עליו ב' היה
שווה. Sela hivvisicha alav beis hayah shaveh. Now this is a more
likely scenario because normally you want the collateral to be more than
the loan. Okay, so I say I lent you a hundred dollars
and it was worth two hundred dollars. והלה אומר... Ve'halah omer... So
therefore, I'm sorry, no, I'm sorry, I don't say that. You, the
borrower, say, "Hey Dov, you know, I borrowed a hundred dollars but
you lost my two hundred dollar משכון. mashkon. So now you owe
me
a hundred dollars." Everybody... by the way, did I say that right?
Yeah. Okay. והלה אומר. Vehala omer. Right, right, right. So now the
לווה loveh is saying the משכון mashkon was more than the loan.
It was two hundred and the loan was only a hundred. You
owe me a hundred dollars. והלה אומר Vehala omer and I the
lender say, "לא כי אלא סלע הלוויתיך ועליו דינר היה שווה. Lo
ki ella sela hivtecha v'alav dinar hayah shaveh. No, it was only
worth a hundred dollars." So now the לווה loveh is saying to
me now that I owe him a hundred dollars and I'm saying
no, we're even. The loan was a hundred, the object was a
hundred, we're even, I don't owe you anything. So I'm a כופר
הכל. kopher hakol. פטור. Patur. Now I'm פטור patur because I'm a
כופר הכל. kopher hakol. סלע הלוויתיך ועליו שנים היה שווה. Sela hivtecha
v'alav shnayim hayah shaveh. Now if the לווה loveh says, "Yes, I
borrowed a hundred but my משכון mashkon was worth two hundred. So
now you, Dov, you owe me a hundred." והלה אומר, Vehala omer,
"לא כי אלא סלע הלוויתיך ועליו ה' דינר היה שווה. Lo ki
ella sela hivtecha v'alav hei dinar hayah shaveh. No, I... yes, I
lent you a hundred but the משכון mashkon was worth a hundred
and twenty-five. Okay? So I only owe you twenty-five." So the לווה
loveh says to me now you owe me a hundred and I
say I only owe you twenty-five. So in that case חייב. chayav.
Okay, so fine. All that is a simple application of you figure
out how much is the net that's being claimed and the amount
that's being admitted, and a כופר הכל kopher hakol is exempt and
a מודה במקצת modeh bemiktzas makes a שבועה. shvua. Okay, one minute.
That's the basic structure there. So far not relevant to us. Let's
keep on reading. Okay, it says,
"חייב. Chayav. מי נשבע?" Mi nishba? Who takes the oath? Now, what
do you mean who takes an oath? If there's a חיוב chiyuv
to make an oath, then it's the person who is being מודה
במקצת. modeh bemiktzas. Right? So it's in each scenario. In the first
scenario, the לווה loveh is being מודה במקצת modeh bemiktzas because I
say the משכון mashkon was not worth so much and there's still
some left of the debt. And in the second scenario, the מלווה
malveh is מודה במקצת modeh bemiktzas because the משכון mashkon was worth
more than the loan, so the לווה loveh is making a claim
against the מלווה. malveh. So the side that is being made the
claim against, the side that's being מודה במקצת, modeh bemiktzas, that's the
side that should make the oath. That's a classic מודה במקצת. modeh
bemiktzas. But here comes the חידוש chiddush of this... of this... of
this teaching.
So who takes the oath? מי נשבע? Mi nishba? מי שהפיקדון אצלו.
Mi shepikadon etzlo. No, the person who takes the נשבע nishba in
all the cases is the מלווה, malveh, the guy who's been holding
on to the פיקדון. pikadon. What does... why? Why if I'm telling
the לווה loveh you still owe me fifty dollars and he says
no I only owe you twenty-five, that should be a classic מודה
במקצת? modeh bemiktzas? He should take the שבועה. shvua. Why is it
that I take the שבועה? shvua? And if I take the שבועה
shvua that he owes me fifty dollars and I'm going to be
the one to collect, why is he going to be the one
to lose out? Let him take his normal שבועה shvua of מודה
במקצת modeh bemiktzas and be פטור. patur. Why do I get to
take a שבועה shvua and win? So מי... so מי נשבע? מי
שהפיקדון אצלו. Mi shepikadon etzlo. Why do I take the שבועה? shvua?
שמא ישבע זה Shema yishba zeh because let's say Michael here takes
the oath that it's only... that the משכון mashkon was worth seventy-five
dollars and he only owes me twenty-five, classic מודה במקצת. modeh bemiktzas.
He takes that oath that it was also... that it was worth
seventy-five and he only owes me twenty-five. ויוציא הלה את הפיקדון. V'yotzi
halaz et hapikadon. But look, all along I'm the one that's holding
on to the פיקדון. pikadon. So I claim that it got lost.
Let's say Michael goes ahead, takes the oath that it was worth
seventy-five and his debt to me is only twenty-five and I say,
"Oh look, look what happened! I just found the פיקדון pikadon and
it's only worth fifty dollars." And I've now proven that Michael here
has made a שבועת שקר. shvuas sheker. So we don't want Michael
to have been sort of... there's evidence to have like... to make
a שבועת שקר. shvuas sheker. I'm going to get to why not
in a minute. And therefore we say better in all these cases
I should be the one making a שבועה shvua because then I'm
not going to find my פיקדון pikadon and prove that I myself
am a liar. Okay, so that's the חידוש chiddush of this... that's
the חידוש chiddush here, that even though it's a מודה במקצת modeh
bemiktzas and the guy who's
admitting to a partial debt is the one that should be making
the oath, it's always the מלווה malveh who makes the oath because
if the לווה loveh makes the oath as to how much the
פיקדון pikadon was worth, the מלווה malveh can always find the פיקדון
pikadon and prove the לווה loveh a liar. Now who cares? Who
cares that the מלווה malveh finds the פיקדון pikadon and proves the
לווה loveh a liar? So we don't want somebody to be proven
to, you know, be a... to be a נשבע לשקר. nishba lasheker.
But you know, he gets what he deserves, right? If he's making
a false oath, so good! It'll make him even more honest that
he knows that the מלווה malveh can always just produce the פיקדון.
pikadon. Why is that such a concern that the guy has a
risk of being proven to be a liar? So תוספות Tosfos says
that we really don't care about the לווה loveh being proven to
be a liar. You're going to take a false oath, you know,
and you're a liar? You get what you deserve. Great. Let Dov
produce the משכון mashkon and prove that you're a liar. The problem
is is that it looks to people that we are imposing oaths
for no purpose. Why is Michael taking the oath about how much
it's worth? Right, I can just go ahead... maybe I have the
משכון mashkon in my house, maybe I'll produce it, and if I
wind up producing it, besides it everybody's going to call Michael a
liar, people are going to say that the בית דין beis din
here was imposing oaths, you know, they... the בית דין beis din
made him take an oath that they didn't have to make him
take because Dov had the משכון mashkon all along. Okay? So since
I've got an incentive in this case... to produce the
משכון mashkon and find it and produce it and so on and
show Michael liar, it'll make the whole process, it'll make בית דין
beis din look bad that we imposed the oath, we made you
take a false oath, whatever, at the end of the day the
משכון mashkon is found anyway. Alright, so that's the חידוש chidush of
this teaching, that the מלווה malveh is always the one who makes
the שבועה shvua and then he's not going to produce it and
prove himself to be a liar. So, and that's, that's how we
handle. Now, how's that relevant for us? So basically, you got the
structure, it's a מודה במקצת modeh bemiktzas based on the net amount
of the loan that's still owed, the money that's still owed, it's
a מודה במקצת, modeh bemiktzas, okay, or in a case where it
is מודה במקצת modeh bemiktzas based on the net amount, then it's
a שבועת מודה במקצת, shvuas modeh bemiktzas, but some of the cases
actually we'll put the שבועה shvua on the other side and allow
us to collect when it's the מלווה, malveh, when it's the מלווה
malveh who is the one will always have the מלווה malveh being
the one that takes the שבועה. shvua. Now how's this relevant for
us? It's relevant for us for the next line. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this, אהיי, Ahay,
at which case is this going on that the מלווה malveh takes
the שבועה? shvua? אי נימא סיפא, Ee-aima seifa, if it's the סיפא
seifa where the מלווה malveh is the מודה במקצת, modeh bemiktzas, the
לווה loveh says you owe me, it was worth 200, you owe
me 100, and the מלווה malveh says I only owe you 25,
it was worth 125, so ותישתבע ליה שבועה גבי מלווה היא. vete-isavei
lei shvua gabei malveh hee.
So you don't have to tell me because of this reason of
making it into a false oath, it's obviously the מלווה malveh takes
the
שבועה, shvua, דקא מודי מקצת הטענה היא, dakamosi miktzas hata-ana hee, he's
the one that's admitting part. אלא אמר שמואל ארישא, Ella amar Shmuel
areisha, obviously we're going on the רישא reisha where the לווה loveh
is the מודה במקצת. modeh bemiktzas. So מאי רישא? mai reisha? What's
the רישא? reisha? סיפא דרישא, seifa dereisha, the second half of the
רישא, reisha, meaning not where the לווה loveh is a כופר הכל,
kofer hakol, he says it was worth 100, I owe you nothing,
no, where he says it's worth 25, I owe you 25, it
was worth 75, I owe you 25.
So in the case where the לווה loveh is a מודה במקצת,
modeh bemiktzas, I say you still owe me 50, he says I
only owe you 25, he should be taking the שבועה, shvua, nevertheless
סלע ופיקדון
על שקר היו שוין והלה אומר לווה סלע ואינו טעון אלא שלושה
דינר היו שוין חייב. sela vepikadon al sheker hayu shavin vehala amrei
loveh sela ve-atani leh shlosha dinar hayu shavin chayav. So that's the
case where you're חייב. chayav. שבועה גבי לווה הוא, shvua gabei loveh
hoo, that the שבועה shvua really should be made by the לווה,
loveh, he's the מודה במקצת, modeh bemiktzas, I say you still owe
me 50, he says I only owe you 25,
ואמר רבנן ישבע מלווה. ve-amar Rabbanan yishava malveh. No, the מלווה malveh
gets to make the שבועה, shvua, I get to make the שבועה
shvua that he still owes me 50 and I get to collect
the full 50, שמא ישבע זה ויוציא הלה את הפיקדון, shema yishava
zeh veyotzi halatza hapikadon, because the לווה loveh will take the שבועה
shvua of 75 and then I'll discover the משכון mashkon and I'll
prove it all false, or I'll make it clear that anyway, whether
it's false or true, the whole שבועה shvua was pointless. Okay, now
why is any of this relevant for us? ואם איתא דרב הונא,
Ve-im itay derav Huna, finally turning to דף ל"ח עמוד א', daf
lamed ches amud aleph, if what רב הונא Rav Huna said is
correct, that the person who says who lost the משכון mashkon always
takes a שבועה shvua דאינה ברשותו, de-eina birshuso, remember that's what we
stopped with, started with, like the person who says, yes, the משכון
mashkon was lost, it was stolen, I'll pay you up, here's the
amount, he says
you still have to swear you're not holding on to it. ואם
איתא
דרב הונא, Ve-im itay derav Huna, if what רב הונא Rav Huna
said is correct, כיוון דמשתבע מלווה
דאינה ברשותו, keivan demishtava malveh dee-eina birshuso,
but the מלווה malveh anyway is going to have to, even when
he's willing to pay whatever, before we get to the whole מודה
במקצת modeh bemiktzas discussion, the מלווה malveh says, oh Michael, I lost
your משכון, mashkon, we're going to have to deduct it from the
loan, and whatever, and then we're going to start fighting how much
was the משכון mashkon worth. But before we start fighting how much
the משכון mashkon is worth, as soon as I say I'm going
to pay you for it, we'll deduct it from the loan, I
have to make a שבועה shvua that I'm not really holding on
to it, right? That's what רב הונא Rav Huna said. So כיוון
דמשתבע מלווה דאינה ברשותו היכי מצי מפיק לה, keivan demishtava malveh dee-eina
birshuso heichi matzi mafik lei, so once I've taken the שבועה shvua
that I'm not holding on to it, then why are we hesitating
having Michael take the שבועה? shvua? Why are we afraid I'm going
to produce the משכון? mashkon? How could I produce the משכון? mashkon?
I already took a שבועה shvua that I don't have it, so
clearly I'm not just hiding the משכון mashkon away. Is this clear
to everybody what's going on here? So let's reframe that. We've got
the case, everybody got the idea that the case about the loan
and the משכון mashkon and the משכון mashkon is deducted from the
loan becomes a מודה במקצת modeh bemiktzas type of a case. The
מלווה malveh who's been holding on to the משכון, mashkon, the reason
the loss of it is deducted is he's essentially a שומר shomer
that is saying I accept responsibility for the loss, right? He's, whether
he's saying I was פושע, posheya, whatever, and we're going to deduct
the loss from the value of the loan. Okay, that's how it
starts, and we'd deduct it, and then we're debating how much of
the loan is left. But according to רב הונא, Rav Huna, we
owe that even when I say I'm responsible, I'm going to take
a שבועה shvua that I'm not holding on to the משכון. mashkon.
So now how come this case we go on to say, if
that's really were true, that when Michael owes me a שבועה, shvua,
he's not going to make it, I'm going to make the שבועה,
shvua, because if he makes the שבועה shvua I might produce the
משכון. mashkon. Why might I produce the משכון? mashkon? I've already taken
a שבועה shvua that I'm not holding on to it, so there
should be no concern.
Wait, before you're swearing?
No, what are you talking about כופר הכל? kofer hakol? Yeah, that
doesn't matter, but I'm not... that's true, whether it winds up being
a case of מודה במקצת modeh bemiktzas or כופר הכל, kofer hakol,
I the מלווה malveh am going to make an oath in every
single one of those four scenarios that I'm not still holding on
to the משכון, mashkon, right?
Oh, well
that's an important factor to have clarified. Yeah, right, in other words
he's always making a שבועה. shvua. Yeah, why should he make a
second שבועה? shvua?
No, it's not about a second one. It's a question about the
משנה, Mishna, here there's four scenarios, right, one where the משכון mashkon
is worth equal or less than the of the other where it's
worth equal or more than the חוב, chov, right? Who's to and
one of us two is a מודה במקצת, modeh b'miktzas, either the
מלווה malveh or the לווה. loveh. Okay, so the and the חידוש
chiddush of what we just taught was
was that was that even when the לווה loveh should be making
the שבועה shevuah and it should be a מודה במקצת modeh b'miktzas
שבועה, shevuah, we're going to reverse it and put it on the
מלווה malveh because the מלווה malveh might be hiding the משכון mashkon
and might want to produce the משכון. mashkon. But if רב הונא
Rav Huna saying is correct, in all four of those scenarios, those
scenarios only begin by the fact that the מלווה malveh says, "I
lost the משכון, mashkon, I'm responsible, I'm going to pay, we're going
to deduct it from the loan." So according to רב הונא, Rav
Huna, in every single one of those scenarios, the מלווה malveh is
making a שבועה shevuah that he's not really lying and holding onto
the משכון, mashkon, that the משכון mashkon is really lost. Okay, so
if he's really if he's starting with a שבועה shevuah that the
משכון mashkon is really lost, then why when it comes to the
מודה במקצת modeh b'miktzas question, do we have to take the שבועה
shevuah away from Michael and put it on me? Right? Because if
Michael were to make it, maybe I'll show that I really am
holding onto the משכון. mashkon. We've already obviated the concerns that I'm
holding onto the משכון mashkon by making me make a שבועה shevuah
at the beginning that I'm not holding on.
So we know we did make a jump. I mean רב הונא
Rav Huna only said his case in terms of a פיקדון. pikadon.
You're saying a משכון mashkon is now a...
A משכון mashkon is a פיקדון. pikadon.
Yeah, I understand, but he's just saying it in that case. Right,
but what we're asking on that case.
Well, that's just an application of the case.
Yeah, no, I understand.
Okay. Why do I still get why am I still getting these
blank stares? I got it. Okay, so we have scenario number one,
which is, okay, the loan was always a hundred dollars. Okay, scenario
number one is that I say the משכון mashkon was worth fifty,
the לווה loveh says it
was
worth a hundred, the net is zero, so you're כופר הכל kofer
hakol and you're פטור. patur.
Okay, the other case is I say fifty, he says seventy-five, the
net is
twenty-five, מודה במקצת. modeh b'miktzas.
Scenario number two. Okay, I say it was worth you he says
it was worth two hundred, I say it was only worth one
hundred, so the net is the net is a hundred. Okay, but
I'm being no, but according to me, according to the מלווה, malveh,
yeah, okay,
it's the same.
Yeah. So this is this is how much does the לווה loveh
owe? Okay? And then this is how much does the מלווה malveh
owe? Okay, so in this case, according to me, I'm the מלווה,
malveh, right? We deduct the hundred from the hundred, I'm saying I
owe zero, so I'm פטור. patur.
And according to this, 125, 200, I say I owe twenty-five and
that's a that's a מודה במקצת. modeh b'miktzas.
Okay, those are the two cases. One is the לווה loveh still
has a part of the loan owed, is he a כופר הכל
kofer hakol or מודה במקצת modeh b'miktzas of part of the loan?
The other is that the משכון mashkon is being claimed to be
worth more than the loan, so is the מלווה malveh wind up
owing any money? Okay, so those are the four cases. The משנה
mishna comes and says that in this case, where he should be
making a שבועה, shevuah, okay, because he's a מודה במקצת, modeh b'miktzas,
we can't have him make the שבועה shevuah because he's making a
שבועה shevuah that how much is the משכון mashkon worth? He's making
a שבועה shevuah it's only twenty-five, and then the מלווה malveh is
going to say, "Oh look, I found the משכון mashkon and you
know, and now the whole שבועה shevuah was pointless or you're" whatever.
So in this case, we reverse the שבועה shevuah and we have
the מלווה malveh make the שבועה. shevuah. Okay, this case we're going
to move from the לווה's loveh column to the מלווה's malveh column
because of a concern that the מלווה's malveh going to produce the
פיקדון. pikadon. And the simple question that we're asking is, in all
of these cases where the משכון mashkon was lost and we're deducting
it from the loan and the מלווה's malveh accepting responsibility, according to
רב הונא, Rav Huna, the מלווה's malveh making an oath that he's
not really holding onto the משכון. mashkon. So since he's making an
oath that he's not holding onto the משכון, mashkon, why do we
have to take this שבועה shevuah away from the לווה? loveh? What
are we afraid of? Okay, the מלווה's malveh already clearly not holding
onto the משכון. mashkon. Is that any clearer? All right, I feel
like, all right, yes.
So for the point of being what I'm not understanding is I
understand the מודה במקצת modeh b'miktzas in the case of a loan,
right? Yeah. Is do I owe you twenty-five, is it really fifty?
I understand, those are indisputable, I mean, if you can say, those
are objective facts. Now, unless your, you know, job is appraising used
iPhones, how are you going to be able to take a how's
anyone going to be able to take a שבועה shevuah on how
much it's worth? You don't know, I don't know, you what you
can do in my mind is say, "All right, well, was it,
you know, you take you say it's cracked so I owe you
less, I say it was, you know, full..." I understand that.
So if we both admit that we don't know, then it's an
אינו יודע. eino yodea. But that's not the scenario. The scenario is
that we're making absolute claims.
You don't know. I don't know as much as you don't know.
You don't know.
Okay, I don't I don't know what to say to you. People
that are in the business of lending of lending money have a
sense about how much these things are worth. Maybe they got maybe
they say I got it appraised Michael, it really is irrelevant. If
people are claiming that they don't know, then it's a different case.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues. So אמר רבא, Amar Rava,
so that's the question. This was all very then... But why are
we concerned that the guy's going to take out the משכון mashkon
if he's making an oath and he doesn't have the משכון mashkon
anymore? So אמר רבא שמא עדים
שנשרפו. Amar Rava shema eidim shenisrafu. Okay, so the reason we're
concerned is because he doesn't need to take a שבועה shrua that
it's not in his רשות reshus because there's witnesses that it's been
destroyed. Of course, אי הכי, ihachi, no, forget what he's saying, they're
showing what it's worth. But אי הכי מהיכא מייתי ליה? ihachi meheika
meisi lei? Why are we afraid that he's going to take out
the משכון? mashkon? You can't say, oh, okay, so we're still afraid
he's going to take out a משכון mashkon because he didn't make
an oath about it because there were witnesses that it was destroyed.
Okay, so why are we afraid he's going to take out the
משכון? mashkon? That doesn't really answer the question, right? אלא אמר רב
יוסף שיש עדים שנגנבה. Ela amar Rav Yosef sheish eidim shenigniva.
Okay, he doesn't have to make an
oath that he's not holding onto it because there were witnesses that
it was
stolen. And therefore, we're still afraid he's going to take it out.
But of course the same question: if there're witnesses that it's
stolen and he didn't have to take an oath that he doesn't
have it, that's all very nice, but why are we afraid he's
going to produce it? And now witnesses that it was stolen. So
the גמרא Gemara says, סוף סוף מהיכא מייתי ליה? sof sof meheika
meisi lei? Where's he going to get it from? Right? Why are
we afraid that he's going to produce it after the שבועה? shrua?
דתירח ומייתי ליה. de-tirach u-maisi lei. No, because he'll go ahead and
he'll start trying to figure find out who stole it from his
house. And then when eventually he
finds it, it'll retroactively have made the whole שבועה shrua moot because
because you know because now we have it and we know how
much it's worth. אי הכי ihachi says the גמרא, Gemara, כי משוה
מלווה נמי ליתרח ליה וליתי? ki meshava malveh nami litrach lo beh
velaisi? So what? Okay, so then how do we let the מלווה
malveh make the שבועה? shrua? If we're saying we're not afraid it's
in the מלווה's malveh closet, okay? א, A, because according to רב
הונא Rav Huna he took a שבועה. shrua. So in order to
get rid of רב הונא Rav Huna we say he didn't take
a שבועה, shrua, there were witnesses that it was stolen. So we're
not afraid it's in the מלווה's malveh closet. But we're still afraid
the מלווה's malveh going to produce it and make the לווה's loveh
שבועה shrua שקר sheker or moot because the מלווה malveh will go
research who stole it and he'll retrieve it. So then how do
we let the מלווה malveh take a שבועה? shrua? The לווה loveh
will go research and retrieve it. So the גמרא Gemara says, no,
בשלמא מלווה ידע מאן קא עייל ונפיק בביתיה. bishlama malveh yodeia man
ka'ayei venafik bevaitei. No, the מלווה's malveh able to figure out who
stole it. He knows who's been in and out of his house.
ואזיל ותירח ומייתי ליה ve-azil ve-tirach u-maisi lei and he'll ask his
neighbors, whatever, he'll go ahead and he'll put in the effort to
retrieve it, especially if it'll help him now with his case against
the לווה. loveh. After the לווה's loveh made a שבועה, shrua, he'll
really, really work to find it so that the לווה loveh made
a שקר sheker and then the whole שבועה shrua will be proven
false. אלא לווה, Ela loveh, but if the מלווה malveh makes the
שבועה shrua we're not afraid the לווה loveh will be able to
find the משכון. mashkon. מי ידע מאן קא עייל ונפיק בביתיה דמלווה?
mi yodeia man ka'ayei venafik bevaitei de-malveh? How does he know who's
going in and out of the house of the מלווה? malveh? Okay,
so basically we said if the מלווה malveh actually took a שבועה,
shrua, then we would not be afraid that then he would produce
the משכון mashkon and prove himself to have been a liar. But
the scenario is that he didn't take the שבועה shrua because there
were witnesses. And nevertheless, we still, because he has more knowledge and
so on, we don't want to let the לווה loveh take the
שבועה shrua now about the value because we're still afraid that the
מלווה malveh might be able to find and retrieve the משכון, mashkon,
even though we started with witnesses that it wasn't in his house.
Yes, question?
Well I was thinking if it's his פיקדון pikadon that he gets
back from the גנב, ganav, but we already established that
what's the question?
About who the גנב ganav is going to pay כפל kefal to?
Well when the מלווה malveh gets the פיקדון pikadon back, it's his
because he paid for the שבועה, shrua, right? So he'd be more
interested in keeping it than
right, I mean, oh, I see.
That's a good point too. You're saying he's got more of an
incentive because since he reimbursed the לווה, loveh, now if he retrieves
it, he's really getting back right, he's recouping his loss. Whereas if
the לווה loveh has no incentive other than the besides the debate
how much it was worth, the לווה loveh has no incentive to
find it because the לווה loveh actually got its value back. That's
a very good point. That's a good point. I wonder why the
גמרא Gemara didn't say it. You're right. The מלווה's malveh incentive to
find it is that by if he finds it, he'll recoup his
loss. It's a very good point.
Yes. Also in the reputation of רב הונא, Rav Huna, right? Who
said the מלווה malveh shouldn't have to make the לווה. loveh.
Right. מלווה malveh doesn't have to make the שבועה. shrua.
The שבועה, shrua, rather. And here we have become or we already
answer, it's like common knowledge the מלווה malveh is doing this whole
investigation, this whole research. If they were only afraid of the impression
that the מלווה malveh was manipulating the system, here he clearly isn't
manipulating the system. He really did not have it, but he went
through the whole טרחא tircha of going and finding it and researching
and asking.
No, no, because that's a possible future scenario. It's not the current
scenario. Right now they're just showing up on our door, it was
a day after the robbery, and they're just debating how much it
was worth. But the point is we're not going to let the
לווה loveh take it because the מלווה malveh might then decide to
go to all that effort and find it.
Regardless of whether he takes it out of his pocket or goes
out and searches for it.
Well, we know he's not going to take it out of his
pocket in this scenario because there were witnesses that it was stolen,
okay? But we're still going to not let the לווה loveh make
the שבועה shrua because if the לווה loveh makes the שבועה shrua
then the מלווה. malveh. might in the future decide to do all
this effort. But we don't know right now what the story is.
Right now it's just a he-said he-said or he-said she-said or whatever
it is. Yeah, but I think the point that was made about
that there's also the incentive of recouping his losses is an excellent
one. It's interesting the גמרא Gemara didn't make that point, yes.
This whole debate that, you know, that we would if the case
was burned you potentially deduct the value of the loan and once
we see that the if you will the משכון Mashkon is already
at the beginning of a pure אונס ones because like you know
if I'm let's say a שומר חינם Shomer Chinam on your משכון
Mashkon and it burns I could say who cares what it was
worth? You still owe me the full value, right? I'm I'm שומר
חינם Shomer Chinam I'm פטור patur from אונס, ones, this is an
אונס. ones.
Yeah, but so that's what I thought, we're assuming that the he
was liable for the loss. Not getting into this question now of
שומר חינם, Shomer Chinam, שומר שכר, Shomer Sachar, whatever.
But deeper math and the way this is structured by this whole
whatever, Michael, you're introducing those are all relevant points, but but whatever,
they're distracting right now.
Okay, אביי אמר גזירה שמא ימצאנה ויאמר לו אחר שמצאתיה. Abaye amar
gzera shema yimtzon viyomar lo achar shehimatztiha. אביי Abaye says, no, no,
no, even if the guy takes an oath, there's a fear that
so I take an oath that it's not in my רשות reshus
and Michael go if if Michael were to take the שבועה shvua
of the מודה במקצת, modeh b'miktzas, how can I then produce it?
I wouldn't produce it, I would be proving myself a liar to
produce it. No, I could still produce it even having taken רב
הונא's Rav Huna שבועה. shvua. How is that? I could say oh,
I thought it was lost, but then my kid was rooting down
in the basement and he found it, so look I found it
and it was only worth 50 it wasn't worth 75. Okay, so
it's possible that I could take the שבועה shvua and still be
able to produce it and still be willing to produce it afterwards.
Maybe I'm lying maybe I'm telling the truth that's a different issue,
but the שבועה shvua of רב הונא Rav Huna is not going
to prevent you know is not going to close out the possibility
that then I will discover claim I've discovered it afterwards.
Okay, so אביי Abaye arguing that in fact the לווה loveh has
to make the שבועה? shvua?
No, we're all agreeing we're all trying to nobody's arguing with הלכה,
halakha, we're trying to make sense of it. Why is it that
we switched it away from the לווה loveh to the מלווה? malveh?
If what רב הונא Rav Huna said is correct that the מלווה
malveh took a שבועה shvua it wasn't in his רשותו reshuso then
we shouldn't be afraid that the מלווה malveh will ever produce it.
And אביי's Abaye answer is no, yes we could be afraid the
מלווה malveh will produce it because even after having sworn it's not
in his רשותו reshuso he could say that he found it afterwards.
Okay, all of this is to explain that the ברייתא braisa assumes
basically works with the assumption that the מלווה malveh could produce it
later. And how would the מלווה malveh produce it later if what
רב הונא Rav Huna said was correct that he swore that it
wasn't in his רשותו? reshuso? אביי Abaye says he could say look
it wasn't I swore I lost it and now I found it.
Okay, רבא אמר זה נשבע וזה נשבע. Rava amar zeh nishba v'zeh
nishba. No,
no, no, you misunderstood the ברייתא. braisa. Really they're both going to
take a שבועה. shvua. Okay, it's not we do not here here's
where he disputes it. We do not move it away from the
לווה. loveh. The לווה loveh makes his classic שבועה מודה במקצת. shvua
modeh b'miktzas. Okay, they're both going to make a שבועה. shvua. זה
נשבע וזה נשבע. Zeh nishba v'zeh nishba. זה נשבע שאינה ברשותו וזה
נשבע כמה שוה Zeh nishba she'eino b'reshuso v'zeh nishba kama shaveh
just like רב הונא Rav Huna said. He says he's not holding
on to it, and since he's not holding on to it we're
not afraid he's going to produce it, and this one swears how
much it was worth because he's the מודה במקצת. modeh b'miktzas. So
how do you read the ברייתא braisa which says that we give
the שבועה shvua to the one who's holding on to the פיקדון?
pikadon? Okay, והכי קאמר, v'hachi ka'amar,
here's how to read it. מי נשבע תחילה Mi nishba techila
who makes the first שבועה? shvua? מלווה נשבע תחילה שמא ישבע זה
ויוציא עליו את הפיקדון. Malveh nishba techila shema yishba zeh v'yotzi elav
et hapikadon. So when the ברייתא braisa said that the מלווה malveh
makes the שבועה shvua because he's holding on to the פיקדון, pikadon,
we don't mean he makes the שבועה shvua of the מודה במקצת.
modeh b'miktzas. We mean the מלווה malveh starts making a שבועה shvua
and starts by saying I'm not holding on to it. Now that
you've told us you're not holding on to it and you're not
going to prove yourself a liar, now we can have the לווה
loveh make the classic שבועה מודה במקצת. shvua modeh b'miktzas. Okay, yeah,
it's clearly not פשט, pshat, but nonetheless it's a good way to
protect רב הונא. Rav Huna. Okay, it is not that we move
the שבועה shvua over to the מלווה's malveh column because מלווה malveh
is making the שבועה שאינה ברשותו shvua she'eino b'reshuso we're not afraid
that he's going to produce it, it's just that he has to
make his שבועה shvua first and then the לווה loveh makes the
שבועה. shvua. Okay, רב הונא בר תחליפא משמיה דרבא אמר רישא דסיפא
תיובתא לרב הונא.
Rav Huna bar Tachalifa mishmei de'Rava
amar reisha deseifa tiyufta l'Rav Huna.
Fine,
so now we're done with sort of that, although clearly the פשט
pshat of that whole case is that there's מלווה malveh is not
swearing that it's אינה ברשותו, eino b'reshuso, we found different ways of
justifying that he was that you know still defending רב הונא. Rav
Huna. Now we're going to now we have another point. Okay, he
says where were we okay רב הונא בר תחליפא משמיה דרבא אמר
רישא דסיפא תיובתא לרב הונא. Rav Huna bar Tachalifa mishmei de'Rava amar
reisha deseifa tiyufta l'Rav Huna.
The first part of the second part okay this case here is
a challenge to רב הונא. Rav Huna. Why? רישא דסיפא תיובתא דרב
הונא. Reisha deseifa tiyufta d'Rav Huna. סלע ופטינה לאו שתים היו שוה
והלה אומר לא כי אלא סלע ופטינך לאו סלע היו שוה פטור.
Sela v'pittina lav shtayim hayu shaveh vehala omer lo ki ela sela
v'pitticha lav sela hayu shaveh patur. Okay this case right the מלווה
malveh says it was only worth 100 he says it was worth
200 he says so he's the מלווה malveh is the כופר הכל
kofer hakol he's פטור. patur. ואי איתא לרב הונא Vee iso l'Rav
Huna but now according to רב הונא Rav Huna in this case
okay the מלווה's malveh totally פטור. patur. The מלווה malveh still has
to make a שבועה shvua of אינה eino Okay, in this case,
the מלוה malveh says it was only worth a hundred, he says
it was worth two hundred, he says the מלוה malveh is a
כופר הכל, kofer hakol, he's פטור. patur. Okay, in this case, the
מלוה malveh says it was only worth a hundred, he says it
was worth two hundred, so he says the מלוה malveh is a
כופר הכל, kofer hakol, he's פטור. patur. והניחא לרב הונא, Ve'niha l'Rav
Huna, but now according to רב הונא Rav Huna in this case,
okay, the מלוה malveh is totally פטור. patur. The מלוה malveh still
has to make a שבועה shvua of אינו ברשותו, eino birshuso, right?
Everybody with me? The מלוה's malveh always going to make a שבועה
shvua of אינו ברשותו. eino birshuso. Okay, so one minute, if what
רב הונא Rav Huna said is right that it's in שבועה אינו
ברשותו, shvua eino birshuso, מיגו דמשתבע מלוה שאינו ברשותו משתבע נמי אגילגול
שבועה כמה היה שוה? migo d'mishtava malveh she'eino birshuso mishtava nami agilgul
shvua kama haya shaveh?
Why is he a כופר הכל? kofer hakol? Why does he get
off without making any שבועה? shvua? He starts by making a שבועה
shvua that he's not holding on to it. Okay, yes, I'll pay
the full hundred, I'm only admitting it was worth a hundred, but
I'll pay the full amount and he makes but he has to
make a שבועה shvua that he's still not holding on to it.
Okay, so now you can't just say you're a כופר הכל kofer
hakol because I mean you are a כופר הכל kofer hakol but
you can't get off without a שבועה. shvua. Once you're making a
שבועה shvua that you're not holding on to it, we can roll
on top of that גלגול שבועה gilgul shvua any other שבועה shvua
we want you to make and we can have you make a
שבועה shvua that it was only worth a hundred and not two
hundred. משתבע נמי אגילגול שבועה כמה היה שוה. mishtava nami agilgul shvua
kama haya shaveh.
That's a really good question. So a lot of evidence here against
רב הונא. Rav Huna. אמר רב אשי, Amar Rav Ashi, says רב
אשי, Rav Ashi, אמריתה לשמעתא קמיה דרב כהנא, amritah l'shmaata kamei d'Rav
Kahana, I said this discussion in front of רב כהנא, Rav Kahana,
ואמר לי, v'amar li, and he said to me, תהא במאמינו. tehei
b'maamino. All right, the case is that the לוה loveh says to
the מלוה malveh in this scenario: You know what? I trust you
that you lost it. I'm not afraid that you're really holding on
to it and lying, okay? And you're just doing it because you
coveted the object. I trust you that you lost it. Now, it's
really stupid of the לוה loveh to say that because by trusting
him and getting him off the hook of the שבועה אינו ברשותו,
shvua eino birshuso, he's losing out on the שבועה shvua here about
their debate of one hundred and two hundred, right? If he would
force him to make the שבועה אינו ברשותו, shvua eino birshuso, he
could do the גלגול שבועה. gilgul shvua. But it's a scenario where
he says, forget it, I waive the שבועה דאינו ברשותו, shvua de'eino
birshuso, we're just going to debate what I don't believe you in
is how much it's worth. Okay, but I do believe you that
you honestly lost it and you're not holding on to it and
coveting it. Okay, but so we're only debating what it's worth and
therefore it's a כופר הכל. kofer hakol. So it was a little
stupid of him because he lost the opportunity for the גלגול שבועה,
gilgul shvua, but that's the scenario. Obviously that's a pretty bad אוקימתא.
ukimta. Let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. ותהימניה לוה למלוה נמי
בהא כמה היה שוה? v'teheymneih loveh l'malveh nami beha kama haya shaveh?
So okay, if you're so trusting of the מלוה malveh that you
don't make him make a שבועה אינו ברשותו, shvua eino birshuso, trust
him when he claims it was only worth a hundred. גמרא Gemara
says: No, קים ליה בגוויה, kim leh b'gaveih, and now Michael can
be happy. No, he figures the מלוה malveh doesn't really know how
much it's worth. It was my object, I really know how much
it's worth. So he may be, I mean, maybe he's an honest
guy, he may be honestly believes it was only worth a hundred,
okay, but he's wrong. I know how much it's worth better than
he does. But I trust him that he didn't, he's not actually
holding on to it.
Okay,
ונהימניה מלוה ללוה דקים ליה בגוויה, v'neheymneih malveh l'loveh d'kim leh b'gaveih,
ונהימניה מלוה ללוה, v'neheymneih malveh l'loveh, לא מהימן. la meheyman. Okay, so
if that's true, if the לוה loveh is such a nice guy,
"You know what, Michael, I trust you, you're an honest guy, you're
not coveting it, you're not holding on to it, you don't have
to make a שבועה אינו ברשותו," shvua eino birshuso, but I don't
trust you it was only worth a hundred, I know better than
you how much it's worth, right? You know, I'm not going to
trust you with that. So now the גמרא Gemara says: One minute,
but if he's so good to me that he's willing to trust
me, why don't I reciprocate the favor? Why don't I trust him?
I say, Michael, it was your object, you know should how much
it's worth better than me. You know, you trust me that I
don't have to make a שבועה אינו ברשותו, shvua eino birshuso, I'm
going to trust you you know better than me how much it's
worth, I'm going to trust you how much it's worth. So why
if the לוה loveh is stupid enough to trust the מלוה malveh
here to waive the שבועה אינו ברשותו shvua eino birshuso and to
give up his advantage of גלגול שבועה, gilgul shvua, why doesn't the
מלוה malveh reciprocate and trust the לוה loveh enough in terms of
how much it's worth? Yeah, but you're also being out money by
trusting me and giving up your advantage. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara
says: So why are we assuming that scenario? ונהימניה מלוה ללוה דקים
ליה בגוויה, v'neheymneih malveh l'loveh d'kim leh b'gaveih, לא מהימן ליה. la
meheyman leh. No,
he doesn't trust him how much it's worth. ומאי שנא לוה דמהימן
ליה למלוה, u'mai shna loveh d'meheyman leh l'malveh, why is the לוה
loveh trust the מלוה malveh and willing to waive the שבועה אינו
ברשותו? shvua eino birshuso? ומאי שנא מלוה דלא מהימן ליה ללוה, u'mai
shna malveh d'la meheyman leh l'loveh,
and the מלוה malveh doesn't trust the לוה loveh how much it's
worth even though the לוה loveh clearly knows how much it's worth
better than the מלוה? malveh? So the גמרא Gemara says: לוה מקיים
ביה במלוה תומת ישרים תנחם, loveh mekayem beh b'malveh tumat yesharim tanchem,
because the לוה loveh thinks that by the מלוה malveh the verse
of
the purity of the righteousness will lead them.
No, I'll tell you in a minute. And מלוה מקיים ביה בלוה,
malveh mekayem beh b'loveh, and the מלוה malveh applies to the לוה
loveh the verse: וסלף בוגדים ישדד. v'selef bogdim yeshaded. I think ישדם.
yeshadem. Anyway, the perversion of the you know of the rebels will
despoil them. Which means what? It means, how come it is that
I am so well off and fortunate and have this money to
lend people money and you נעבעך nebach are going around borrowing money
from people? It must be that God likes me better than you.
This actually was a very widespread theology in the ancient world which
is, you know, it's funny because it's almost very against a lot
of whole Jewish theology, you know, that people that are well off,
it's because it's a proof of their righteousness.
Not against us.
Well, no, this פסוק pasuk does
not prove well maybe. I mean, okay, there's all שכר ועונש. s'char
v'onesh. It's true, I mean, in one way there's all this whole
שכר ועונש. s'char v'onesh. it was basically that you look at poor
people as deserving their being poor and it's also alleviating you of
a responsibility towards them, you know, clearly the wealthy are favored by
God, the poor are despised by God. So basically, so Michael says
Dov must be a good guy, I mean, how else did he
get so wealthy? It must be he was totally always scrupulously honest
in business, right? And that's why God likes him. So therefore I'm
going to trust Dov, but I say to Michael, this poor guy
who's gone around borrowing money, he must be dishonest, he must not
be a good guy, I'm not going to trust him how much,
you know, how much the object is worth. So anyway, that's the
way he gets to explain the scenario that the שבועה shvua got
waived because the לוה loveh trusts the מלוה, malveh, but the מלוה
malveh is not willing to pay the amount because the מלוה malveh
doesn't trust the לוה. loveh. Anyway, almost all this whole proof shows
that, seems to show that Rav Huna is wrong, you know, we
had a lot of תירוצים, terutzim, but the simple sense throughout is
that there's no שבועה אינה ברשותו, shvua eino birshuto, and nevertheless, you
know, Rav Huna still asserts his position. Yes.
I don't understand, so the only counter is to how much it's
worth? Like I can't pay you don't know, I mean I could
only counter with another value, right?
No, you could say you don't have an idea
and then it's a question about, you owe me a hundred dollars
and
I say איני יודע, eini yodea, and then it becomes a whole
question, you want me a hundred dollars and I say איני יודע,
eini yodea, or I say I don't know how much you owe
me and I say you only owe me whatever, so then it
plugs into those, so then just plug that in, okay, then that's
the whole debate about how much is owed where one side claims
איני יודע. eini yodea.
Alright, yeah, so where does the theology come in that you pushed
back with that says about the person who gets money in this
world, it's because...
Yeah, so that's pretty much, that's how חז״ל Chazal basically deal with
all the injustice in the world, right, that's, you know, but Rabbi
Dov is correct, I mean, this in a certain way is a
biblical theology, you know, so, okay, although, you know, the Torah never
translates that into how we look at other people, that's the only
thing. Meaning the Torah says like, you know, if you do this,
you'll get your rains in their right time and you'll be rewarded,
and you know, and there it speaks more about extremes rather than
sort of the normal income variation that occurs within a society, right?
The Torah doesn't say that if you do the מצוה mitzvah you'll
be wealthy, and if you don't, then you'll be poor, right? I
mean it talks more about, you know, it talks more about, so
it's not even really biblical theology. Right, right, the Torah accepts there's
a reality that there's always going to be a poor, there's always
going to be a range in society, whatever. So to sort of
see this, even this, I think that this theology goes beyond the
Torah שכר ועונש s'char va'onesh theology. Okay, but...
Isaac gets a hundredfold and Abimelech says Hashem must have blessed you.
Oh, that's true. I mean you do have that, right, you do
have sometimes that people that are wealthy get very, you know, people
are blessed. I mean the whole idea of a ברכה bracha could
be a ברכה bracha prosperity. I still think it's a little different
than how one looks at the poor within the society, but you're
right, I mean, it's not coming out of nowhere. Okay, but certainly
against חז״ל's Chazal's theology. Okay, הוה גברא דאפקיד כיפי גבי חבריה. Hahu
gavra d'afkid kifi gabei chavrei. A certain person, now let's crank, let's
shift gears. A certain person entrusted
some jewelry by his friend. אמר ליה הב לי כיפי, Amar lei
hav li kifi, and then he said to him, okay, give it
back to me, the jewelry I asked you to watch for me.
אמר ליה לא ידענא היכא אותבינהו, Amar lei lo yadana heicha otveinhu,
I don't know where I put them, I lost them, I misplaced
them. It's not I lost them, lost them is I left them
in the train station, this is like I have lost them in
my house, I misplaced them. Okay, אתו לקמיה דרב נחמן, Atu l'kamei
d'Rav Nachman, came to Rav Nachman. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so Rav
Nachman said, כל לא ידענא פשיעותא היא. Kol lo yadana peshiuta hi.
Anything which is I don't know where they are, that's negligence, okay,
so they're lost, they're lost to the owner, I don't care if,
you know, they're just misplaced, the difference at a certain point between
misplaced and lost is not big. So anyway, they're lost, you don't
know what you did with it, that's negligence, זיל שלים, Zil shalim,
go pay, even if you were just a שומר חנם, shomer chinam,
go pay. לא שלים, Lo shalim, he refused to pay, or he
didn't. אזל רב נחמן אגביה לאפדניה מיניה. Azal Rav Nachman agbei l'apadnei
minei. So Rav Nachman went and he seized the guy's castle.
He repossessed the house.
He repossessed the, yeah, he took, right, exactly. He repossessed the house.
לסוף אישתכח כיפי, Lesof ishtakach kifi, in the end, the jewelry was
found. ואיקור, V'eikur, and then the value had gone up of the
jewelry. Okay, so אמר רב נחמן, Amar Rav Nachman, so now the
owner wants the jewelry back and is willing to give back the
house that was seized as collateral.
אמר רב נחמן הדר כיפי למרייהו, Amar Rav Nachman hadar kifi l'mareihu,
let the jewelry go back to the owner, והדר אפדנא למריה, v'hadar
apadna l'marei, and let the house go back to its owner. אמר
רבא, Amar Rava, alright, הוה יתיבנא קמיה דרב נחמן, Hava yativna kamei
d'Rav Nachman, I was sitting in front of Rav Nachman when this
case came for him, ופרקין המפקיד הוה, u'pirkin Hamafkid hava, and we
were learning המפקיד, Hamafkid, our פרק, perek,
it's always fun when the גמרא Gemara is sort of self-referential, right?
Okay, and we were learning המפקיד, Hamafkid, ואמרי ליה, v'amri lei, and
I said to him, I quoted him a משנה, Mishnah, שלם ולא
רצה לישבע, shilem v'lo ratza lishava, when a guy is agreed to
pay, then he gets כפל. kefel. So he assumed that what this
teaches is not just that the guy gets כפל, kefel, but that
he really winds up as, you know, what's it said before, owning
the object, he effectively bought the object by paying, okay, and we
discussed earlier that he doesn't get גיזוז וולדות, gizoz v'vladot, he might
not get retroactively. you know, like the shearings or whatever, but first
of all this isn't retroactive. This is an increase in value after
he paid. He effectively bought the jewelry. And then afterwards, it increased
in value. Okay? And this is all also more like כפל kefel
that it's more seen as like an external sort of increase rather
than a natural produce of the object like the גיזה gizzah and
the ולדות. vlados. So he says look, he paid, he basically buys
the object. That's why he gets כפל. kefel. He should be entitled
now to keep the jewelry and to get the increase. Okay? So,
so that's what I challenged him with. ולא אהדר לי v'lo hadar
li and he didn't respond to me, he ignored me. ושפיר עבד
דלא אהדר ליה, v'shappir avad d'lo hadar leih, he was right to
ignore me. Why? מאי טעמא התם לא אטרחה לבי דינא הכא אטרחה
לבי דינא. mai ta'ama hatam lo atrecha l'vei dina hacha atrecha l'vei
dina. Ah. And now we're seeing another factor which sort of came
up before. Before one factor was also the issue about
how much does the,
how much did you do a favor for the original owner? How
much is he willing to be מקנה makneh you the object? There
were the interpersonal aspect. But here it's more the greasing of the
wheels of the בית דין. beis din. It's more from that perspective.
And one of the reasons your paying makes you own the object
and get the object and get the כפל kefel and here get
the increase is because you made things go very quickly. You just
were willing to pay and we were willing to deal with the
case and move right along. Here you refused to pay and we
had to go through the בית דין, beis din, we had to
go seize it. Now what's interesting though, you didn't refuse because you
denied your liability. It doesn't seem like he said, "oh I wasn't
פושע, poshea, I'm going to take a שבועה shvua that it was
an אונס". oness It doesn't matter. You might have admitted your liability
but you still forced us to do it through the court. And
once you force us to do it through the court you lose
your benefit of paying. Your paying is that you're willingly paying or
agreeing to pay, not that you're being forced to pay. Forced to
pay is not the case of our משנה. mishnah. Okay?
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
One minute, fine, it's not the case of our משנה, mishnah, but
there's still another problem. The other problem is let it not be
the case of the משנה. mishnah. Once בית דין beis din seize
this guy's house, that was the payment of the debt. So forget
our משנה. mishnah. Once the payment is made, the משנה mishnah says
it's like you retroactively owned it and you get כפל kefel from
the time it was stolen. Forget the משנה. mishnah. Once you paid
it, the debt was paid and the other side now owns the
פיקדון. pikadon. He paid for the פיקדון, pikadon, right? He lost it,
the debt was paid, so the other side owns it. So let's
deal with it at that level. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this.
למימרא l'meimra says the גמרא, Gemara, one minute, הכא דסבר רב נחמן
דשומא הדר. hacha d'savar Rav Nachman d'shuma hadar. Does that mean that
when property is assessed in payment for a debt, it can be
reversed? So let's take the classic example. Classic example of that is
Michael owes me a thousand dollars. I want him to pay cash.
He doesn't have cash. Okay, we have to go to the court.
The court assesses that Michael's, what do you have, I guess now
we'll have to, watch. Michael's beautiful watch is worth a thousand dollars.
Okay, and they seize it for me and they give it to
me in payment of the debt. Now a few weeks later, a
month later, Michael manages to put together his thousand dollars. He has
a thousand dollars cash. Can he get his watch back or do
we say the debt's already paid off? That's the question of שומא
הדר. shuma hadar. Does assessed property that was seized in payment of
the debt, can that be bought back by the
original debtor, by the borrower? Because in the end of the day,
really I only wanted money. So if he eventually gives me money,
can he buy back the object that was seized? Or is it
no, once it was that, was given, it was payment of the
debt. Yes, we have seen this before. So the fact that we
are allowed to now reverse it, Michael's
allowed to say,
"here's the house back for the jewelry", we're allowed to reverse it,
doesn't that show that שומא הדר? shuma hadar? So the גמרא Gemara
says, where were we? למימרא דסבר רב נחמן דשומא הדר. l'meimra d'savar
Rav Nachman d'shuma hadar. That when something is assessed and seized like
in the case of the watch or in the case of the
house and then the original thing, the money or the object or
whatever was found, that it can be reversed? So does it seem
to be that that's what you're saying, right? That it was, that
we're reversing it now? No. גמרא Gemara says no. שאני התם דשומא
בטעות הוא דהוה כיפי מעיקרא. shani hatam d'shuma b'ta'us hu d'hava kifi
mei'ikara. No, no, no. There, in a normal case, we know Michael
owed me the thousand dollars. There was no mistake. He owed me
a thousand dollars, he didn't have the money, this was in payment
of the debt. In the other case, why was the house seized?
The house was seized because it was assumed that the jewelry was
lost. But at the end of the day, once we find the
jewelry, we really realize that there was no need to make that
payment. That you can give back the original object. The object was
never lost, there was no debt that the שומר shomer ever incurred.
Is that clear? If the object was always around, the שומר shomer
really didn't incur the debt because there was no real loss to
the owner. It was misplaced, but there was no real loss, there
was no real debt. So that's why... Now it can be reversed.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: אמרי נהרדעי, Amri
Narda'ei, and now נהרדעי Narda'ei says שומא הדר תריסר ירחי שתא, shuma
hadar treisar yarchei shata, that in the normal case of property seized
in payment of a debt you can buy it back up till
12 months. Okay, because really you shouldn't, as we're about to see,
you really shouldn't be ever allowed to buy it back. That was
payment of the debt, end of story. Okay, but he says no,
no, no, actually up for a year the borrower can buy it
back.
ואמר אמימר, Va'amar Amemar, אמימר Amemar says, אנא מנהרדעי אנא, ana mi-Narda'ei
ana, I'm from Narda'ei, דסבירא לי de-sevira li and I'm of the
opinion that שומא הדר לעולם, shuma hadar le-olam, that you can always
buy it back, which is really bad news for me. I now
seize Michael's watch, okay, and like I have to be aware that
like I, you know, I mean a better example would be I
seize Michael's property in payment of a debt, like how, what am
I supposed to do? I can't develop the property because anytime he
gets his money together, he's going to buy it back from me.
That's like really bad news for the מלווה. malveh. So let's take
a look. והלכתא לשומא הדר לעולם. Ve-hilchata le-shuma hadar le-olam. Yes, it
does always go back, which is crazy. Why? משום שנאמר ועשית הישר
והטוב. mishum she-ne'emar ve-asita ha-yashar ve-ha-tov. It's not really, legally it makes
no sense. Michael owed me a thousand dollars, the property was payment
of that thousand dollars, that's it, he paid off his debt, he
paid off his debt in property. Okay, it's not like the case
of the שומר shomer we dealt with before where it turns out
that he really didn't owe me any money because the object never
had really been lost. He really owed me the money, this was
real payment of debt, that should be the end of it. But
it's the right thing to do is to give it back to
Michael because at the end of the day, at the end of
the day, I lent him money and I only really was entitled
to getting money back. Okay, and therefore, and he, you know, and
he never really wanted to give me property, so therefore, and that
was just because he didn't have the cash on him. So the
right thing to do would be to let him get his property
back once he can give me the money. Now of course, that
puts me in an impossible situation because now I can't develop, I
can't do anything with it. The other fascinating thing is, is that
we are taking a ethical principle of ועשית הישר והטוב, ve-asita ha-yashar
ve-ha-tov, and normally we speak about the letter of the law and
the spirit of the law, and here we're turning the spirit into
the letter. And here we're basically saying in this case, because it's
the right thing to do, even if it's not, he doesn't have
any legal rights here, we're going to make it the legally mandated
thing to do. Okay, and then we're going to now sort of
talk, spin out the applications, implications, yes.
Okay, so a couple things. So one is, this is essentially say
that for this extended 12-month period of time...
not 12 months, we just said it's לעולם. le-olam.
Yeah, well I was out. So okay, oh that's right, so it's
לעולם, le-olam, that's right, sorry. So
it's essentially the item becomes a פקדון pikadon until the...
Yeah, the problem is, that's all great if it's 12 months. 12
months is one thing, I'll hold onto it for 12 months, give
you a little more time to buy it back. But לעולם le-olam
is completely destroys the מלווה's... malveh's... this will wreak havoc on the
whole lending system.
Right, so my second question, but the מלווה malveh gets to keep
whatever שבח, shevach, no? In other words, there would be like...
Yeah, that...
yes, that would be true, that because this is not דין, din,
because this is ועשית הישר והטוב, ve-asita ha-yashar ve-ha-tov, the מלווה malveh
does get any improvement. So you in a way you're right, which
is is that if I go ahead and I do develop the
land, then Michael and he retrieves it, he he would have to
pay me the difference. That could be true,
that's true, and that would explain why it's not make this impossible,
you know, but nevertheless, you know, if it turns out, you're right,
you're right, it's not impossible because he would still have to pay
me the difference. But it still obviously creates a big problem, you
know, whatever cog in this in this system.
Does that extend to the kids too?
Yes, so that's what the גמרא's Gemara's going to say. פשיטא, Peshita,
so now we're going to spell out the implications about this about
buying back property that really was paid off in payment of a
loan. פשיטא שמה ליה לבעל חוב ואזל איהו ושמה ליה לבעל חוב
דידיה. Peshita shama leh le-ba'al hov ve-azal ihu ve-shama leh le-ba'al hov
dideih. Now I went ahead and I seized Michael's property, okay, and
but the thing is that I owed דב Dov also a thousand
dollars. So after I seized Michael's property of a thousand dollars, then
דב Dov came ahead and he seized it from me to pay
off the debt that I owed him a thousand dollars. Okay, so
אמרינן ליה, amrinan leh, and then Michael finally gets his money back,
so Michael can go buy it back from... we shouldn't say דב,
Dov, too many דב Dovs here. עטרה, Atara, I owe עטרה Atara
a thousand dollars. She goes ahead and she takes it from me
after I took it from Michael. Michael gets his thousand dollars together,
he can go buy it back from עטרה. Atara. Why?
Because
לא עדיפת מגברא דאתית מיניה, lo adifat mi-gavra de-atit mineih, you're no
better than דב, Dov, you took it from דב, Dov, דב Dov
would have had to give it back to Michael, you have to
give it back to Michael. Now part of the reason we're going
to see is, is because she also fundamentally is only entitled to
money. It's all really about money. The property is because money wasn't
available. So now if she can get the money back the same
way Michael can give me the money and get it back, Michael
can give her the money and get it back. However, זבנה או
אורתה או יהבה במתנה, zabnah o ortah o yahavah be-matanah, let's say
instead I sold it, or I gave it as a gift, or
the guy died and he bequeathed it to his kids, right? In
those cases, that was given as property, it wasn't given in payment
of cash, it was given to the final receiving property receiving party
as land, right? If I went ahead and gave it
to עטרה Atara as
a
gift. I want this land and she received it as land. In
that case, nobody, Michael is entitled to come and give her a
thousand dollars and take it back, okay? So in that case,
ודאי הני מילי אדעתא דארעא נחית ולאו אדעתא דזוזי נחית. vada'i hani
milei ada'ata d'ara nachis v'lav ada'ata d'zuzei nachis. So then right, so
in the cases where she's going for the land and not for
the money and Michael cannot give her the money and take it
back. So you got it? Or he doesn't have to. If it's
a מלוה, malveh, the מלוה malveh basically lent money and is basically
is entitled to money. So therefore we say, if the guy can
produce the money, he's entitled to get it back. Not entitled, but
ועשית הישר והטוב v'asita hayashar v'hatov he gets it back, okay? Even
from a second מלוה, malveh, even like the Mike, even if if
I owed money to עטרה, Atara, but in the end it was
all about money, so he's entitled to get it back. But for
anybody for whom it was given to as a plot of land,
then they don't have
to, they have no moral obligation from ועשית הישר והטוב v'asita hayashar
v'hatov even to have to give it back.
Right. Now by the way, if I'm smart, here's what I'm going
to do. I'm going to seize it from Michael, I'm going to
sell it to עטרה Atara and then buy it back from עטרה.
Atara. That's what I would do if I was smart. Okay, I
don't know if I could do that, but that's the obvious thing
that I would do, okay?
Everybody got that? As soon as I sell it to עטרה, Atara,
it's off limits. Now she's got land, now I'm buying it from
her, I'm buying it as land, so right, that's the way I
would do it. Anyway, okay.
Doesn't it get pierced as a...
Yeah,
I don't know. I'd have to find that out, but that's the
first thing that occurred to me. Okay, now, okay, זוזי נחית. zuzei
nachis. So שמו לה לאשה ואינסבא. shamu lah l'isha v'insva.
Now let's say it was seized from a woman and then the
woman got married, okay? או שמו מינה דאשה ואינסבא o shamu minah
d'isha v'insva
or...
Meaning is her marriage like a transaction? Is that...
Yeah, well we're going to right, when the husband gets rights to
the property.
Okay, or the woman I've got to make sure I'm doing this
in the right direction.
Or the woman, wait, no, I think the first case is the
woman was owed the money
and so Michael owed this money to a woman, and then it
was assessed and she seized it, and then the woman got married.
Or the other case is שמו מינה דאשה, shamu minah d'isha, the
woman owed the money, so the woman was and her property was
assessed and seized by the creditors. ואינסבא v'insva and then she got
married ומתה umetah and she died. Okay, so the question is, what's
her husband's status?
Is this in the second case?
In both cases. בעל בנכסי אשתו לוקח הוי לא מהדרינן ולא מהדרי
ליה. ba'al b'nichsei ishto lokeach havei lo mahadrinan v'lo mahadri lei.
So if, so the husband is considered a purchaser and not an
heir, and therefore he doesn't give it back and we don't give
it back to him. Which means what? If, when, in the case
where the woman
seized Michael's property, got married, okay, died, okay, and now Michael has
come up with the money, all right? And he wants to buy
and he wants to get it back from the husband. We say
sorry, the husband who inherited his wife, he's treated not just as
an heir but a purchaser, okay, as somebody who purchased the property
and you can't get it back, as we've just established, from the
person who purchased it from the from the woman who seized the
property from you. Is that clear, right?
Even if she was the heir, we said ועשית הישר והטוב v'asita
hayashar v'hatov either way it wouldn't work?
You're right, even by ירושה, yerusha, you're right about that. So the
real reason we have to say this, that's a good point. The
real reason we have to say this is in the other case,
which is, is that the woman owed money to Michael, Michael went
ahead and seized her property, she married a guy, she died, and
now the husband has a thousand dollars and wants to buy it
back from Michael. We would let the heirs buy back their father's
property because they're considered a continuation of the father, so the right
of the person to buy back his property would pass on to
his heirs, but the woman's right to buy back her property does
not pass on to her husband. Her husband is seen as a
לוקח, lokeach, not as an heir. But you are right, from the
other perspective, whether an heir or a לוקח, lokeach, right, the property
is now protected, it's not to be retrieved. Okay, so how do
we know this? דאמר רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא באושא התקינו אשה שמכרה
בנכסי מלוג בחיי בעלה, d'amar Rabbi Yosi berabi Chanina b'Usha hitkinu isha
shemachra b'nichsei milug b'chayei ba'alah, a woman who sells in her the
property that her husband is has the rights to the fruit and
she owns the title to, while her husband is alive, ומתה umetah
and then she dies, הבעל מוציא מיד הלקוחות, haba'al motzi miyad halokochot,
the husband can retrieve it. So why does this prove that he's
a purchaser and not an heir? Because if a father sells property
and he dies, then as then the kids don't have the property.
If all you are is an heir and your father sold it,
then you're out of that property. But if the woman sells the
property and she dies, the husband can retrieve can take it back,
because basically the status we give the husband in his wife's property
is not just an heir when the woman dies, but it's like
from the very beginning of the marriage he's already purchased the property,
you know, under the condition that the woman dies and so on.
So since he's considered a purchaser and the first purchaser of the
property, if the woman sells it and then she dies, he retrieves
it not as an heir but as the first purchaser of the
property. So the relevance of that for us
is...
When she dies. Right. Okay, I know it's 8:30. Are people willing
to give me three minutes and we can get finished to the
משנה? Mishnah? Let's at least finish to the
משנה. Mishnah. אגביה בחובא. Agbei b'chovoh. Now let's say, okay, back to
the case that
now that I went ahead and I seized Michael's property not through
the court system. Michael, you owe me $1,000, I know Dov, I
don't have it, here take this little plot of land. Okay? And
we didn't involve the court. So now you would think Michael's being
such a good guy, he didn't involve the court, all the more
that he's going to have a right to buy it back, right?
But actually law does not always work that way about who's a
good guy. פליגי רב אחא ורבינא. Pligi Rav Acha v'Ravina. Rav Acha
and Ravina debated it. חד אמר הדרא, Chad amar hadra, that in
that case Michael also can buy it back. וחד אמר לא הדרא,
V'chad amar lo hadra, he can't buy it back. מאן דאמר לא
הדרא סבר, Man d'amar lo hadra savar, האי זביני מעליא היא. hai
zvini maalya hi. Since the court didn't have to seize it from
Michael, so when Michael gave it to me, he was of his
own free will essentially selling me the land for the thousand dollars.
That was just a normal transaction. You sold me your land for
the thousand dollars you owed me. That's it, end of story. When
it was seized against his will, we feel bad for poor Michael,
he wanted to give the money but we seized the property, it
was taken away from him, let him buy it back. But here
he's being such a good guy, he's giving it, so it's a
completely legitimate transaction. We don't feel bad for him. Okay, which is
so ironic. Okay, דאדעתא דנפשיה אגביה. D'ah meidaiteh d'nafsheh agbei. It was
done, you know, willingly. ומאן דאמר הדרא, U'man d'amar hadra, no he
can still buy it back, סבר לא זביני מעליא הוא, savar lo
zvini maalya hu, it was not really a sale. דהאי דאגביה מדעתיה,
D'hai d'agbei meidaiteh, the fact that Michael was willing to give me
the property without involving the court, ולא אתא לדינא, v'lo ata l'dina,
we didn't have to come to the court, מחמת כיסופא דאגביה. machmat
kisufa d'agbei. He was embarrassed. He said, what, I'm going to have
the sheriff come and seize my property, whatever, you know, I'll give
it to Dov, I won't make a public thing about it. Okay
fine. So therefore it's really true, I mean, it's a little ironic
that he's such a nice guy, but nevertheless, you know, sometimes nice
guys finish last, okay? And therefore even based on ועשית הישר והטוב,
V'asita hayashar v'hatov, if he did it willingly, maybe he loses his
right to go ahead and buy it back. ומאימת אכיל פירות? U'me'eimas
achol peiri? Now at what time can do I, I seize Michael's
property and took it, at what time is it considered do I
own it? And do I get to benefit from it and get
the fruit of it? Okay, whether or not he buys it back,
Dov is right, he buys it back but I still got the
benefit during the interim. Okay, when do I start being considered the
owner of that property to get the benefit? רבה אמר מכי מטי
אדרכתא לידיה. Rabba amar michi mati adrasta l'yadei. From the time I
get basically the writ from the court that entitles me to his
property, then I own the property. אביי אמר בחתימתו. Abaye amar b'chasimaso.
I don't even have to physically get it, once it's signed I
have the right to that property. What does that mean? What's signed?
The court signs the document that gives me the right to a
plot of land. Even before they hand it to me. ורבא אמר
מכי שלמי ימי אכרזתא. V'Rava amar michi shlimu yemei achrazta. No, that
even after the document is signed, there's a whole auctioning period. And
so that we can get the best price for the property and
somebody could offer more and then they would get it and I
would take the money and they'd take the property. So until the
whole auctioning and announcing period is over, I don't yet own it.
Once that period is over, then I own it and then although
Michael still might have a chance of buying it back. Okay.